<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Constantinople in the Vines of Perah, at the funerall of the vertuous and admired Lady Anne Glouer, sometime wife to the honourable Knight Sir Thomas Glouer, and then ambassadour ordinary for his Maiesty of Great Britaine, in the port of the Great Turke. By William Forde Bachelour in Diuinitie, and lately preacher to the right honourable ambassadour, and the rest of the English nation resident there. ...</title>
            <author>Ford, William, b. 1559.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102518</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838296</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838296</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2670</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01069)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2670)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1065:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Constantinople in the Vines of Perah, at the funerall of the vertuous and admired Lady Anne Glouer, sometime wife to the honourable Knight Sir Thomas Glouer, and then ambassadour ordinary for his Maiesty of Great Britaine, in the port of the Great Turke. By William Forde Bachelour in Diuinitie, and lately preacher to the right honourable ambassadour, and the rest of the English nation resident there. ...</title>
                  <author>Ford, William, b. 1559.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 82, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edvvard Griffin for Francis Constable, and are to be sold at his shop at the white Lyon, ouer against the great north doore of Sainte Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-I⁴ M² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Glover, Anne, --  Lady, d. 1608.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2670:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2670:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT CONSTANTINOPLE, in the Vines of PERAH, at the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the vertuous and admired Lady ANNE GLOVER, ſometime Wife to the Honourable Knight Sir THO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAS GLOVER, and then Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour ordinary for his Maieſty of GREAT BRITAINE, in the Port of the Great Turke. <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM FORDE <hi>Bachelour in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, and lately Preacher to the right Honourable Ambaſſadour, and the reſt of the Engliſh Nation reſident there.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Death. </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Teares. </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Pilgrimage.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of</hi> The Graue.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by EDVVARD GRIFFIN for <hi>Francis Conſtable,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the white Lyon, ouer againſt the great North doore of Saint <hi>Paules. Anno Dom.</hi> 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2670:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2670:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRED ACCOM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLISHT AND VERTVOVS beautified Lady the Lady WENTVVORTH, Wife to the moſt noble and moſt worthy of all honours, and all titles, LORD, the Lord WENTVVORTH.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon
<note place="margin">The <hi>Turke</hi> permitteth Chriſts Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; the Pope conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it to the racke and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition; who is the better man?</note> (moſt vertuous and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: Lady) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued at firſt in the Vines of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> adioyning to renowned <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boll
<pb facs="tcp:2670:3"/>or great Citie of the great Turke; and there deliuered (inſteed of a faire Temple) in a pleaſant Garden, vnder a lofty Cypreſſe
<note n="*" place="margin">A Tree fit for ſuch aſſemblies for the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents were wont to beare the branches therof in their Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals.</note> tree, in a goodly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of diuers Nations
<note n="*" place="margin">There were preſent of moſt Nations vnder the Sunne, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, French, Dutch, Germain, Italian, Popiſh, Hungarian, Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiluanian, Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da: Wallachian, Ruſſes, Greekes, Armenians, Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowines, Turkes, Iones,</hi> &amp;c.</note>, after long trauaile through many and ſtrange Countries, is now at length by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious fauour of the Almightie, footed in <hi>Great Britaine;</hi> where thinking to haue repoſed it's wearied limbs, is by gentle intreatie moued, and forcible im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie ouer-ruled, to beginne a new trauaile, to vndertake a new iourney, viſite many Cities, enter many houſes, paſſe through many hands, offer it ſelfe to many quicke-ſighted eies, ſubmit to many cenſorious heads. As therefore in her firſt birth ſhe had to ſhadow her fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sunnes ſcorching beames, a beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and umbriferous Tree; ſo ſhe nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:2670:3"/>ſome pleaſing Canopie, ſome refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing <hi>vmbrello</hi> to ſhadow her ſtil. And vnder whoſe wings may ſhe better ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and maintaine her ſelfe (moſt ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous and honour: Lady) then vnder yours? you were the Patroneſſe of the Lady whom ſhe honoureth, whoſe life ſhe relateth, whoſe death ſhe lamenteth, whofe Funerall ſhe celebrateth; you, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with your honourable and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<note n="*" place="margin">The Lady <hi>Croft.</hi>
               </note> Mother, gaue that Lady her bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, communicated vnto her your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, aduanced her to her honours; ſo that the beſt of her life, her education, her vertues, her honours, ſhee deriued (next vnder God) from you: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being dead, her wandring obſequies haue recourſe vnto you for protection, preſuming that for loue you bare vnto the liuing,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruth</hi> 2.20.</note> you will not ceaſe to doe good
<pb facs="tcp:2670:4"/>vnto the dead; the good you ſhall do her is to daigne that your honourable name (as it was a Sanctuarie vnto her ſelfe while ſhe liued) ſo it may patronage her Funerals being dead. It is not I, for what am I vnknowne to you, or my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruings? but ſhee, or becauſe ſhee is not, I for her, or rather her liuing ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues for her dead ſelfe, that imploreth this gratious fauor at your gentle hands. Your tender breaſt wil not deny ſo hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a ſuter; your olde loue will bid you yeeld to a deſire ſo zealous. In full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence whereof I haue ventured to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixe your honourable name, which, if it find (as it feruently deſireth) accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance fauourable, it ſhal perhaps encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage mee to ſecond it with ſome more pleaſing and delightfull ſubiect, which mine owne experience hath gathered
<pb facs="tcp:2670:4"/>from no leſſe painefull then farre for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne obſeruations. In the meane ſeaſon my deuoted heart ſhall deuoutly pray for length of daies, redoubled ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, graces happineſſe, to deſcend and reſt vpon your vertuous head, and after this life the eternall crowne of a better life.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in the moſt humble deſire, and tender of his ſeruice and obſeruance, WILLIAM FORDE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:2670:5"/>
            <head>EPITAPHIVM.</head>
            <p>VIator ſiſte paululum, hic manes te monent vt mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, haec citus lege, ac tacitus luge; ſi iuſsa obibis mea, domum demum tui memor abibis: In hoc tumulo, terrae cumulo, omni virtute cumulata, tumulata iacet <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> imo potius Agna (hoc ei enim nomen vt &amp; omen etiam fata dederunt) <hi>Anna Lamb,</hi> manna dulcior, Agna mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior &amp; amicior, in <hi>Anglico</hi> ſolo concepta, nunc in Caelum &amp; Angelicum chorum recepta; quae illuſtriſsimo Domino <hi>Thomae Glouer,</hi> apud hanc Ottamannoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> portam <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae Britaniae,</hi> &amp;c. Legato regio nupta, ſe tam mite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ei Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitem praebuit, vt cum eo tanquam luna ſolem ſuum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quens, &amp; curſum ſuum varijs terra marique erroribus flatibus &amp; fluctibus inuicta, non communi ſed coeleſti or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine perſiciens, ab occidente in Orientem, lata, ecclipſim, terra hac (vt vides) interpoſita, paſſa ſit, breui lucem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am receptura, non perit enim, quae meliorem vitam reperit: Sed du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Libitinae libet, quotquot adſumus, abſumus. Nos humiles imo humus ac fumus coelos nil caelare poſſumus, &amp; natura nimis interdum matura quod boni offert, cito au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert, quamuis aliâs longior etiam mora mori alios non ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat. Haec volui a te meme volui, in quibus ſi te recte ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſces, mihi certe paucula haec ignoſces, <hi>Vale.</hi> Etperge.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2670:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Gen. <hi>23.</hi> ver. <hi>2.3.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Then Sara died in Kiriatharba the ſame is Hebron in the land of Canaan. And Abraham came to mourne for her, and to weepe for her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>3.</hi> Then Abraham roſe vp from the ſight of his Corps and talked with the Hittites ſayinge.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>4.</hi> I am a ſtranger and a forrener among you, giue me a poſſeſſion of buriall with you that I may bury my dead out of my ſight</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or a ſorowfull meeting, what more meet, then wordes, and ſongs, and ſobs, and ſighes of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe? ſpeech with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, matter with action, action with affection, affection with occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhould ſympathize together. We haue here before our eyes a ſad ſpectacle, a hearſe couered with Sable weedes, a cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin filled with wormes and aſhes; fitting
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2670:6"/>for which obiect, we haue ſingled out a doleful text, which doth intreat of nought but woes and ſorrowes, of death, of teares, of pilgrimage, of the graue. Of death, by the power of ſinne triumphing ouer life; of teares, as the fruits of ſinne weeping at the power of death; of pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, as the lot of life trauelling vnto death, of the graue, as the home of pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes and the houſe of death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then Sarah died.</hi> Here is the power of death triumphing ouer life? And <hi>Abraham</hi> came to mourne for her and to weepe for her, here are the fruits of ſinne weeping at the power of death. Then <hi>Abraham</hi> riſing vp, ſaid vnto the Hittites, <hi>I am a ſtranger and a forrenner among you,</hi> here is the lotte of life, which is a pilgrimage vnto death. <hi>Giue me a poſſeſſion of buriall with you,</hi> here is the home of pilgrimes and the houſe of death</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then Sarah died.</hi> Thence obſerue, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall condition of mankinde, euen that which the Apoſtle hath confirmed
<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> 
               <hi>It is appointed vnto men that they ſhal once die.</hi> And
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2670:6"/>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> came to mourne and weepe for her, thence obſerue, that naturall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards the dead is commendable in all, Then <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid <hi>I am a ſtranger and a forrenner among you.</hi> Thence obſerue, that all men are but ſtrangers and pilgrims here on earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Giue me a poſſeſſion of buriall with you.</hi> Thence obſerue, that the dead are to be honoured with buriall and a graue.</p>
            <p>That all men muſt once die, that naturall affection towardes the dead is commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all, that all are but pilgrims and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers here on earth, that all after death are to be honoured with buriall &amp; a graue, are the foure ſad ſeuerall ſubiects, of my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing ſad diſcourſe, which whiles I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie to this ſad ſpectacle, applie you your hearts to ſorrow, your eyes to teares, if not for her that is dead and gone (for ſhe is bleſt and reſteth from her labours) yet for your owne ſinnes, which will cauſe you (will you nill you) God knowes how ſoone, looke you how well, to follow after her, we will by Gods aſſiſtance and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2670:7"/>your much deſired patience, trauiſh the ſame ground we haue began to tread, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the ſteppes, and following the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in the ſelfe ſame order we haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then Sarah died.</hi> Was <hi>Sarah</hi> the firſt that died; was not mother <hi>Eue</hi> with her daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and her daughters daughters dead long before: if dead, and why not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned? what was rare and ſingular in <hi>Sarahs</hi> death, that ſhee alone aboue all other women, aboue <hi>Eue</hi> her ſelfe ſhould deſerue to haue the firſt memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, then <hi>Sarah</hi> died: ſurelie I know no other reaſon but this, that as <hi>Abraham</hi> was the father ſo <hi>Sarah</hi> was the mother of the faithfull, and therefore the holie Ghoſt vouchſafeth vnto her, that which he denied to other women before her, an honourable mention both of her age, how long ſhe liued and of the tyme of her death, when ſhee died, when <hi>Sarah</hi> was an hundreth twentie and ſeuen yeeres olde, ſo long liued ſhe, then <hi>Sarah</hi> died <hi>Sarah</hi> though the mother of the faithfull,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2670:7"/>though a holy and religious matrone, though a Saint of God yet then Sarah died.</p>
            <p>Whence we obſerue the generall condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankinde.</p>
            <p>It is appointed vnto men that they ſhall once die, all muſt drinke of <hi>Sarahs</hi> cup, the cup is full of one and the ſame liquour, the liquour is drawne from one and the ſame fountaine, the fountaine it ſelfe is poiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and if the fountaine be vncleane the ſtreames will be troubled too, if the root be cankred the branches will wither alſo, if the head be diſeaſed, the members will be diſtempered too, Now the head, the roote, the fountaine, as of <hi>Sarah</hi> ſo of all mankinde, was father <hi>Adam,</hi> as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Adam</hi> by ruſhing againſt the law like a pitcher that daſheth againſt the wall, ſinned not onlie in his owne perſon, but in his humane nature, not onlie in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe but in his deſcent, ſo he purchaſed the puniſhment of ſinne which is death, not onlie vnto himſelfe, vnto his owne perſon, but vnto others, vnto his humane
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2670:8"/>nature, of which we all partake. For as by one man ſaith the Apoſtle, (by one <hi>Adam</hi> and one <hi>Eue,</hi> two in ſex, but one in nature, one in mariage, one in ſinning, the woman ſeduced by the Serpent, the man induced by the woman, (ſinne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the world, and death by ſinne, <hi>ſo by the ſinne of one man, death went ouer all men, in whom all men had ſinned,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.</note> But how did ſinne enter by one into the world; not by propagation of kinde onlie, as <hi>Socinus</hi> the hereticke auerreth, but by participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the fault alſo, and by imputation of the guilt; And how did death enter by ſinne? euen as an effect that followeth yts cauſe, or as a ſhadowe that accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth a bodie in the ſunne. And how went death ouer all; as a plague <hi>graſſantis in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,</hi> depopulating the citie or a houſe where it entereth: or like an enemie <hi>pervagantis, vaſtantis, ſternentis,</hi> raging ranging, deſtroying, all that he meets with, or like a hidden, poyſon that diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it's venome, vnto euery member, and penetrateth vnto all and euerie part,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2670:8"/>not onlie vnto a few ſicke weaklings, and poore ſtaruelings, but generallie vnto all, high and lowe, rich and poore, bond and free, of what age, ſex, condition, degree ſoeuer; all, men and women, young and old, great and litle, ſtrong and weake, are ſubiect to deaths ſtroke whence the poet cryeth out.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heu mortem inviſam quaeſola vltricibus armis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elatos fraenas animos, communia toti</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Genti ſceptra tenens, aeternaque faedera ſeruans,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quae magnos parvoſque teris, quae fortibus aequas</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Imbelles, populiſque duces, ſeniumque iuventae.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Maphaeus,</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>True it is indeed that which Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> taught long agoe, God at firſt created man as a meane betweene Angels and beaſts, that if he obeyed the Lord his true creatour and kept his heſtes, he might be tranſported to the Angels ſocietie, but if he became peruerſe in will, and offended the Lord his God, then that he might be caſt vnto death like a bruit beaſt; And to this end he placed him in the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> the paradiſe of God, ſtored with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2670:9"/>matchleſſe varietie, of whatſoeuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes heart could deſire, eſpeciallie gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed begnets hacaim, with the tree of life, and begnets haddagneth the tree of knowledge, which two trees he appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him for two Sacraments, by the tree of life myſtically importing that if he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his obedience, he ſhould ſurely enioy life, neuer feele nor feare hunger, thirſt, ſickenes, age, or death, by the tree of knowledge that if he tranſgreſſed the commandement, <hi>ipſo facto</hi> In the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry act
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> 
               <hi>moth tamuth dyinge dye.</hi> he ſhould moſt certainlie die, or he ſhould die a double death, the death of the body, &amp; the death of the ſoule which accordingly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, as had beene threatned, for in the ſame houre he began to eate, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to die, not onelie a ſpirituall death, which is a ſeperation of man from God, who is the life of man and the length of
<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 30.</note> dayes, vnto which and vnto which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the hereticke <hi>Socinus</hi> reſtraineth it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceating the death of the bodie to be a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quele, not of ſinne but of nature, euen of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2670:9"/>of nature vncorrupted, ſo that the body ſhould haue died though man had neuer ſinned, but alſo and not onelie (as <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> erroneouſlie thinketh) a corporall death, which is the diſſolution of nature, and the ſoules laſt farewell vntill the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall reſurrection vnto the bodie which actuall diſſolution though inſtantlie it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed not, yet was to be ſeared euerie moment, for as in ciuill iudgements &amp; Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridicall proceedings among men, a man condemned to death, though after his condemnation he be committed vnto the Iaylour, by him caſt againe into the dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, and there linger for a long time a dying life, yet in common eſteeme he is rather reckoned among the dead, then the liuing, and we are wount to ſay of him ſentence is paſt, he is a dead man: In the ſame manner <hi>Adam,</hi> from the verie day and houre he receiued his ſentence of mortalitie <hi>gnaphar attah, vel gnaphar thaſhubh,</hi> earth thou art, and into the earth thou ſhalt returne, though after this, the line of his life were long extended, yet the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2670:10"/>nature of his life was but a death, becauſe he was dead in doome, for he that makes himſelfe lyable vnto puniſhment, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der puniſhment <hi>ſi non re, tamen ſententia</hi> if not in deed yet in doome. And in this reſpect ſaieth Saint <hi>Ambroſe, Adam</hi> from the verie act of his eating the forbidden fruite, may be rightly ſaied to haue died inſtantlie, becauſe he neuer after liued one day, houre, or moment, wherein he was not obnoxius vnto death, we commonlie ſay of them that haue ſuckt in ſome ſtrong and violent poyſon, <hi>actum est,</hi> he is a dead man, becauſe though as yet he breath, yet ſtay a little and loe he is ſtone dead: So may we ſay of <hi>Adam,</hi> and as of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo of euerie ſonne of <hi>Adam,</hi> who haue all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſinne of <hi>Adam, hic mortuus eſt,</hi> he is a dead man, becauſe though as yet he liue, yet hauing dranke his deadlie bane he muſt ſurelie die.</p>
            <p>For euer ſince the ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> as ſoone as man beginnes to liue, hee begins a perpetuall iourney vnto death, And there is none ſaieth Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> but is nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2670:10"/>death at the yeeres ende, then he was at the beginning, to morrow then to day, to day then yeſterday, by and by then iuſt now, and now then a litle before, each part of time (if time haue partes) that we paſſe, cuts of ſo much from our life, and the remainder ſtill decreaſeth,
<note place="margin">Auſten in Pſal. 127.</note> 
               <hi>veniente pueritia</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſten moritur infantia, veniente adoleſcencia moritur pueritia, veniente iuventute moritur adoleſcentia, veniente ſenec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute moritur iuventus, veniente morte moritur omnis aetas,</hi> when childhood commeth on, infancie dieth, when adoleſcencie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth childhood dieth, when youth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth adoleſcencie dieth, when olde age commeth youth dieth, when death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth all and euery age dieth, ſo that looke how many degrees of ages we deſire to liue ſo manie degrees of death we deſire to die, aske an olde man where is his infancie where is his childehood? where is his ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſcencie? where is his youth? ſhal he not ſay true if he anſwere, alas all theſe are dead and gone, what ſpeake I of ages? e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie yeere, moneth, day houre, of our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2670:11"/>life that we haue liued, is dead to vs, and we are dead with them, what therefore elſe is our whole life, but a long death. what is euery day therof but as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 5.</note> Petrarch ſaieth a degree vnto death, what is euerie moment therof but a motion vnto death? whence it is that
<note n="*" place="margin">In regiſtro.</note> Gregorie compares the life of man vnto a Saylour in a ſhippe, for as he that ſayleth whether he ſtand or ſit, or lie or walke, is alwayes wafted onwards by the motion of the ſhippe: ſo it is with vs, whether we wake or whether we ſleepe, whether we walke or whether we talke, whether we ſit or whether we lie, whether we will or whether we nill, by times moments we are caried forewardes vnto our ende, and as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 24.</note> Seneca ſaieth <hi>quo tidie morimur</hi> we die euery day; for euery day we looſe part of our life, <hi>&amp; tunc quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que cum creſcimus vita decreſcit</hi> and our life, euen then decreaſeth when it increaſeth Paralel with that of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>lib. Solil.</hi>
               </note> Saint <hi>Auſten vita mea qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tò magis creſcit, tanto magis decreſcit, &amp; quanto magis procedit tanto magis ad morte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit,</hi> my life the more it increaſeth the more
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2670:11"/>it decreaſeth the more it is lengthened the more it is ſhortned, and the longer I liue the nearer I approach vnto death, For all our life indeede is but a liuing death, or to make the beſt of it, it is no better then a continuall paſſage vnto death, wherein one can neither ſtay nor ſlake his pace, but all runne in one and the ſame manner, with one and the ſame ſpeede, for the ſhort liuer runneth his race no faſter then hee that liueth long, both runne alike, both make ſpeede alike, the difference is, the firſt hath not ſo farre to runne as the later. It is one thing to runne further, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to runne faſter, he that liues long runneth further, but not a moment faſter, euerie man haſteneth vnto death alike though one haue a leſſer way to goe then the other.</p>
            <p>And hence it is that though all men make equall haſt yet all haue not the ſame arriuall vnto death, but ſome in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, others in the noontide, others in the euening of their age, yet all in ſome one houre or other. For howſoeuer there
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2670:12"/>may be ſome difference of tyme, yet there is no vncertaintie of the ende, but ſooner or later it is certaine all ſhall come to an end.
<note place="margin">Iob. 30.23.</note> 
               <hi>I know aſſuredly,</hi> ſaith holy <hi>Iob, thou wilt bring me vnto death, which is the houſe appointed for all the liuing, as a hauen for all ſhipping.</hi> It may be when a ſhip is come to the mouth of the hauen, a blaſt driueth it backe againe: but thither it will arriue at the laſt, ſo muſt wee, all of vs, at the gates of death, <hi>Omnes</hi> (ſaith the Poet) <hi>vna manet mors, &amp; calcanda ſemel via laethi,</hi> Death is the end of al, and once the way of death is to bee troad of all. For as all ſtarres moue from the Eaſt to the Weſt, and all the riuers runne into one Sea ſo all men trauel vnto one home, the houſe of death, which therefore the
<note n="*" place="margin">1. King. 2 Ioſh. 23.14</note> Prophet in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbiall manner calleth the way of all the earth. And as all trees haue their death, either they fall through the tempeſts of windes, or rend in ſunder through the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of thunder, or wither away through the length of time:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 51.6.</note> ſo all on earth are mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. <hi>All fleſh,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>waxeth old
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2670:12"/>as a garment;</hi> a garment whether it bee worne or whether it lie folded in a cheſt, periſheth at length, if it bee not worne it will ſoone bee motheaten, if worne, it will ſoone into ragges. And as the leaues on a thicke tree, ſome fal, and ſome grow: ſo is the generation of fleſh and bloud, one is borne, and another dieth: which the Heathen Poet well ſaw,
<note place="margin">Homer.</note> though hee himſelfe were blind, in that verſe of his, which <hi>Pyrrhus Eleenſis</hi> aboue all other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſo much commended:</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Tale genus eſt hominum quale eſt folioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſuch is the generation of men as of leafes, ſo one periſheth &amp; commeth to his end, and another riſeth vp in his place. And as the leafe buddeth, ſpringeth, floriſheth, wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth old and withereth away: ſo man is borne, groweth, floriſheth, waxeth old, and vaniſheth away; and as many leafes are nipped in the bud: ſo many men are cut of in their youth, <hi>tale quidem genus eſt hominum quale eſt foliorum.</hi> So then ſuch as a leafe is, ſuch is a man; there is no leafe but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2670:13"/>at length withereth, and there is no man but at length dyeth; the wind bloweth, and the leafe fadeth, death with his peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous breath approacheth, and man dieth. Who can ſtopp the wind that it blowe not? who can hinder death that it come not?</p>
            <p>What one writeth wittilie of the Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marian is true of euerie ſonne of <hi>Adam,</hi> that being able to decline all other nounes in euerie caſe, could decline death in no caſe. there was neuer Oratour ſo eloquent that could perſwade death to ſpare him, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Gibber ſo mightie nor monarch ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that could withſtand him. <hi>Nerus</hi> the faire Therſcites the foule, Selym the cruell, Solyman the magnificent, Craſſus the rich, Irus the poore, Damaetas the peaſant, Agamemnon the Prince, all fall downe at deaths feet, if he command, we muſt away, no teares, no praiers, no threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, no intreatings will ſerue the turne: ſo ſtiffe, ſo deaſe, ſo inexorable is death.</p>
            <p>There are meanes to tame the moſt fierce and ſauage beaſts, meanes to breake
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2670:13"/>the hard marble, and to mollifie the Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, but not any one thing to mittigate deaths rage, <hi>Reſiſtitur,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſten, ignibus, vndis, ferro, reſiſtitur regibus, reſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Imperijs</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Aug. Pſa. 121.</note> 
               <hi>venit vna mors &amp; quis ei reſiſtit?</hi> Fire, water, the ſword, may bee reſiſted, and Kings and Kingdomes may be reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, but when death commeth who can reſiſt it? <hi>non miſeretur inopum</hi> (ſaith
<note n="*" place="margin">Ber. de conu. cler.</note> Saint <hi>Bernard) non reueretur diuitas,</hi> Death pitieth not the poore, regardeth not the rich, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not the mightie, ſpareth not any.</p>
            <p>It is in mans power indeed to ſay vnto death,
<note place="margin">Polydor.</note> as ſometime King <hi>Canutus</hi> ſaid vnto the Sea, when it beganne to flow. Sea I command thee that thou touch not my feet: but his command was bootleſſe, for he had no ſooner ſpake the word, but the ſurging waue daſhed him: So may man ſay vnto death when it approcheth, Death I command thee not to come neere me: but no force, death will ſtrike him, and no more power hath man to keepe backe death that it ſtrike not, then the mightieſt King on earth to keepe backe the Sea that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2670:14"/>it daſh not. The Sea will haue his fluxe, and death will haue his courſe, <hi>antiquum obtinent,</hi> they both keepe their old wont, ſince the firſt diuiſion of waters, the Sea hath beene accuſtomed to ebbe and flow, who hath euer hindred it? and ſince the firſt corruption of nature, death hath been accuſtomed to ſlay and deſtroy, who hath reſiſted it? Other cuſtomes haue and may be aboliſhed, a King may command, and it is done; but what Monarch ſo abſolute? what Emperour ſo potent, that could a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogate in his dominions this cuſtome of dying? It was a cuſtome among the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginians to ſacrifice humane fleſh, but this cuſtome is aboliſhed. It was a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome alſo among the Indians to eat mans fleſh, but this cuſtome is aboliſhed too, many other inhumane and vnnaturall cuſtomes in the world haue beene, but they are or may be aboliſhed. But this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of dying, there was neuer yet any Prince, ſeene, read, or heard of, that could aboliſh. For this condition which the Wiſe-man ſaith,
<note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 14.</note> is the condition of all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2670:14"/>times remaineth ſtill, Thou ſhalt die the death, no man, no meanes can aboliſh it.</p>
            <p>No not length of dayes, nor wiſedome, nor riches, nor honour, nor beautie, nor ſtrength, no not that excellent grace and gift of holineſſe and pietie. The Antient, Fathers and Patriarches before the floud liued very long, ſome 700. ſome 800. ſome 900. yeeres and more, and yet at length of all and euery one the concluſion is, he died. <hi>Salomon</hi> was a wiſe King, the wiſeſt that euer was, hee knew the nature of all ſimples, from the very Hyſope to the Cedar, and therefore if any, ſurely hee aboue others could haue preſerued himſelfe from death, and yet of him it is ſaid in the end, he died.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sampſon</hi> was indued with extraordinary ſtrength, at one time hee ſlew a thouſand with the iaw bone of an Aſſe, and yet hee dyed. <hi>Dauid</hi> was a man after Gods owne heart, and yet he died. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw God face to face, and yet hee died. The Prophets were indued with a great meaſure of ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, yet the Prophet
<note n="*" place="margin">Zach. 1.5</note> 
               <hi>Zachary</hi> ioines
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2670:15"/>them all together in one ſtate of mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, your Fathers where are they? and do the Prophets liue for euer? What ſay I the Prophets? Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe the Sonne of God, the onely ſonne, the Sonne in whom hee was well pleaſed, more wiſe then <hi>Salomon,</hi> more mightie then <hi>Samſon,</hi> more holy then <hi>Dauid,</hi> and all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, though hee knew no ſinne in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, yet for taking on him the burthen of our ſinnes, became ſubiect to the ſame condition of mortalitie with vs, and hee dyed alſo. And that I goe no further, but come home vnto my Text, <hi>Sara</hi> who liued a hundred twenty and ſeuen yeares, and was as the Hebrewes myſtically expound the numbers, ſo chaſt and innocent at twenty yeares old, as ſhe was at ſeuen, and ſo faire at a hundred yeares old, as ſhe was at twenty; yet neither her wiſedome, not her beauty, nor her chaſtity, could ought auaile her: but heere you ſee the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, <hi>Then Sarah died.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any ſhall obiect, but <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> died not, I anſwere, we know not, I rather
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2670:15"/>thinke they did, and that <hi>Elias</hi> in his fiery Chariot had his bodie burnt, and <hi>Enoch</hi> who in his yeeres matched the dayes of the ſunne 365. was without paine diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued when God tooke his ſoule to heauen, or if they died not, yet as <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith, the generall is not therefore falſe, becauſe GOD hath diſpenſed in ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, though one or two died not, yet this is an vniuerſall truth of all men to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and duely pondered. It is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto men that they ſhall once die.</p>
            <p>And is it indeed
<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> appointed vnto men that they ſhall once die? Is there but one way for all the earth to goe, one doore, deaths
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Kin. 22</note> doore, for all the liuing to turne into? how neerely then doth it concerne vs, to bethinke our ſelues of this way, to fit our ſelues for this iourney, and euen in this life, to take care for another life, a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter life, eternall life. A man that knowes for certaine hee muſt reſigne his dwelling houſe, within a moneth, or a weeke, or a day, is very ſilly and ſimple, if he take no order for procuring ſome other habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<note n="*" place="margin">Iob 30.23</note>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:2670:16"/>that when he is put out of his owne houſe, he may haue another to couer his head in: ſo will it bee with vs, who inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite theſe houſes of clay, whoſe foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the duſt,
<note n="*" place="margin">Iob. 4.</note> we know for certaine wee ſhall leaue them, how ſoone wee know not, perhaps to morrow, perhaps to day, perhaps this very houre, we are ſilly then and vnprouident, if wee take no care for prouiding other houſes. What ſaid
<note n="*" place="margin">Ser. 2. dedi. Eccl.</note> Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> to his ſoule, <hi>Ad huc domum quidem habes (O anima) ſed certa eſto, quoniam in bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>caſura eſt domus tua, &amp; niſitu pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideris aliam, erís pluviae, vento, &amp; frigori ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponenda.</hi> O my ſoule thou haſt yet a houſe to dwell in, but be aſſured thy houſe will ſhortly fall and moudre, and vnleſſe thou prouide thee before hand of ſome other houſe, caytiue, forelorne and naked ſhalt thou be expoſed vnto the winde, the raine, and the cold: alas, who can ſtand in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of this ſtormy tempeſt; happy ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, thrice happy ſhalt thou be my ſoule, if then thy conſcience tell thee, thou canſt ſay vnto thy ſelfe in faith and full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2670:16"/>
               <hi>I know that if my earthly houſe of this Tabernacle be deſtroyed, I haue a building giuen of God, that is, an houſe not made with hands, but eternall in the heauens,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>Againe, is it appointed vnto men that they muſt once die? Oh that wee could euery one of vs (as we ought) ſeriouſly conſider this, and daily and duly ponder with our ſelues, of this theame, We muſt die. Doubtleſſe this vvould cauſe vs to feare God vvhile vvee liue, that vve might finde fauour at his hands vvhen vvee die. <hi>For who ſo feareth the Lord, it ſhall goe well with him at the laſt, and he ſhall finde fauour at the day of his death</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 1.</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It would moue vs to imbrace the good, and refuſe the euill, remembring that as <hi>Precious is the death of the Saints in the ſight of the Lord:</hi> ſo euill is the death of ſinners
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 34.</note>.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It would abate in vs the plumes of our pride, and humble vs farre below the Niniuites, and <hi>Ahab,</hi> conſidering that <hi>Earth we are, and into earth we ſhall returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and why art thou proud O earth and aſhes</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 10.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2670:17"/>
            <p n="4">4. It would worke in vs a true remorſe and ſorrow for our ſinnes, laying before our eyes the ſaying of our Sauiour, <hi>Vnleſſe you repent alſo you ſhall likewiſe periſh</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 13.</note>.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It would breed in vs a diſtaſte and diſlike of earthly things, <hi>Facile enim contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit omnia,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ierome, qui ſe cogitat mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riturum,</hi> as <hi>Eſau</hi> when hee was ready to die for hunger contemned his birthright, <hi>En morior quid mihi proderunt primogenita,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ge. 25.32</note> Loe I am almoſt dead, what is then this birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right to mee? whereas contrariwiſe, they that dreame of a long life treaſure vp to themſelues in earth
<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. It would expell out of our hearts rancor and hatred, procure loue and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, reunite and reconcile vs to our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, whiles we are in the way
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 5</note> ſeeing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement will be too late when wee are once deliuered to the Iaylor.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It would make vs watchfull of our wayes, and learne vs <hi>Dauids</hi> praier: <hi>Lord, let me know mine end, and meaſure of my dayes what it is,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 39.</note> 
               <hi>let me know how long I haue to liue,</hi> and why would hee know this? <hi>That hee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2670:17"/>might apply his heart to wiſedome, for in the graue there is none, O Lord, that remembreth thee</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 6.</note>.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Laſtly, this conſideration that we muſt once die, would be a good motiue vnto vs to learne by time how to die, for that which at length wee muſt neceſſarily doe, we will if wee be wiſe learne by time how to doe, among all other works which we are to doe: to die, though it bee the laſt, is not the leaſt.
<note place="margin">Euripides &amp; Seneca.</note> Yet miſerable (ſay two learned Hethens) a thing it is in the houre of death not to know how to die.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore, Chriſtian brethren, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al things labour for this knowledge, whiles we liue let vs learne how to dy, that ſo when death ſhall ſpread his pale colour ouer our faces, we may intertaine it not in horrour; but in honour, not as a loſſe; but an aduantage, as a doore opening to ſaluation, not a gate leading to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now if you ſhall aske me, but how muſt we learne to die? I will lead you to another of your owne profeſsion, to an ancient Hermite for an anſwere. It hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2670:18"/>that a Marchant man (like your ſelues) trauelling through a Forreſt, eſpied neere a little Cell, an olde Hermite of whom he was inquiſitiue to know what hee made there? The Hermite anſwered, My ſonne I learne to die.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mar.</hi> What needes that, ſeeing whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou wilt or no thou muſt ſhortly die? <hi>Her.</hi> And this is that troubleth me, ſeeing I muſt ſhortly die, and yet I know not how to die. <hi>Mar.</hi> But what is it to know how to die? <hi>Her.</hi> To know how to die is to eſchew euill, and doe good, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Declina a malo &amp; fac bonum. Mar.</hi> Father, what doeſt thou eate that thou art ſo long liued? <hi>Her.</hi> I eat the beſt meat. <hi>Mar.</hi> But who prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it? <hi>Her.</hi> The beſt Cooke, hunger. <hi>Mer.</hi> What are thy meditations and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes? <hi>Her.</hi> I call to minde the time paſt, conſider in the bitternes of my ſoule, how I haue ſpent my former yeeres, and where I find that I haue done wel I thanke my God, where ill, I ſorrow and repent <hi>Mer.</hi> Art thou rich? <hi>Her.</hi> I haue more
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2670:18"/>then I would, to wit, this bodie of mine. <hi>Mer.</hi> What then, wouldeſt thou die? <hi>Her.</hi> I would willingly die well that I might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine eternall life. <hi>Mar.</hi> Canſt thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct me how to die well, and to liue eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally? <hi>Her.</hi> I can, vvhat is thy profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? <hi>Mer.</hi> I am a Marchant. <hi>Her.</hi> If thou vvilt play the true Marchant, and buy the greater for the leſſe, the better for the vvorſe, looke vp to heauen, behold it is better and greater then the vvhole earth, ſell all and buy that; ſell thy ſins, ſell thy pleaſures, ſell thy profits, buy this one Iewell, and to this end, caſt thy bread vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the vvaters, make thee friends of the vnrighteous Mammon, by doing good: now the good vvhich the Lord requireth of thee is (as the
<note n="*" place="margin">Mica. 6.</note> Prophet vvitneſſeth) <hi>To doe iudgement, to loue mercy, and walke with the Lord our God,</hi> this doe and thou ſhalt haue eternall life. <hi>Mer.</hi> So may I liue as I follow thy counſell: Farewell. <hi>Her.</hi> Goe in peace.</p>
            <p>Theſe and the like good fruits, good motions, good affections, the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2670:19"/>of our end &amp; diſſolution would ingender in vs, and happy, yea thrice hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, are they that thus conſider. And to ſet you forward herein, conſider I beſeech you, conſider with your ſelues vvhat you are? vvhat your life is? What you are, the Poet telleth vs, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Man is a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, a dreame, or a dreaming ſhadow. What your life is, dailie experience ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<note n="*" place="margin">Iam. 4.14</note> 
               <hi>It is a vapour that ſoone vaniſheth,</hi> a drie leaſe carried with euerie winde, a ſleepe fed with imaginarie dreames, a Tragedie of tranſitorie things, it paſſeth awaie like a poſt in the night, like a ſhip in the Sea, like a Bird in the aire, whoſe tract the aire cloſeth: concerning the ſhortneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the Heathen Poet could ſaie, A man is but a man of a daie old, the kinglie Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaid, it was but a ſpan long; <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaie, It is a life of daies; <hi>Iob, Eſay, Paul,</hi> compare it to a bubble, a ſleepe, a booth, a ſhepheards tent, vvhich euerie daie is renewed: yea, they come ſo farre at length, that they compare it to a thought, whereof there may bee a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2670:19"/>in one day. But what need we theſe reſemblances, ſith wee can turne our ſelues no waie, but ſomething there is which may put vs in minde of our morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. Can you enter your Counting hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and caſt eie vpon your houre-glaſſe, and not conſider that as the houre paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, ſo doth our life? Can you ſit in your chaires by the fire ſide, and ſee a great quantitie of vvood turned into ſmoake and aſhes, and not conſider vvith the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, <hi>Sic in non hominem vertitur omnis homo,</hi> So man, no man will ſuddenlie become? Can you walke forth into the fields, and ſee how ſome graſſe is comming, ſome new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vvithered, ſome alreadie come, and not conſider vvith the
<note n="*" place="margin">Eſa. 40.6</note> Prophet, <hi>That all fleſh is graſſe, and all the graſſe thereof is as the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the field?</hi> Can you feele the aire moue and the winde beat in your faces, and not conſider the breath of man is in his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, ſtop his
<note n="*" place="margin">Eſa. 2.22</note> noſtrils, and his breath is gone, and that the ſtrongeſt tenure of your life is but by a puffe of vvinde? Can you ſit on the riuers bank, &amp; not conſider
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2670:20"/>that as the riuer runneth, and not retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, ſo doth your life? Can you ſhoot in the fields, and not conſider, that as the arrow flieth in the aire, ſo ſwiftlie doe your daies paſſe? Or if wee be like Horſe and Mule without vnderſtanding to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this, yet I am ſure wee cannot bee ſo ſenſeleſſe, as not to conſider that which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie daies light preſenteth to our view.</p>
            <p>To daie our ſuperiours, to morrow our inferiours, next daie our equalls, one vvhile our friends, another while our foes are taken from vs, and life from them. And maie not the ſame happen vnto anie one, or euerie one of vs, which happeneth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, are we more free then they? It is a good compariſon of one who likeneth death vnto an Archer that ſhootes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time beyond vs, not ſparing our ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, ſometime ſhort of vs ſtriking our inferiours, ſomtime at our right hand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuing vs of our friends, ſometime at our left hand hitting our foes, and now and then it hits the marke it ſelfe, and wee are dead as well as others.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:2670:20"/>
            <p>And ſurelie if we goe no further then our owne ſelues, and conſider how manie diſeaſes we continuallie carrie about vs, what aches affect our bones, what heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe our bodies, what dimneſſe our eies, what deafeneſſe our eares, what trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling our hands, what rottenneſſe our teeth, what balneſſe our head, what grai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes our haires. All and euerie one of theſe, as ſo many loud alarums would ſound vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, Death is neere: or if none of theſe did affect vs within, yet how many thou ſand dangers doe daily threaten vs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and ſeeme to ſhew vs preſent death? <q rend="inline">Goe into the ſhip,
<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> there is but a foots thickneſſe betweene thee and death. Sit on horſebacke in the ſlipping of one foot, thy life is in danger: goe through the ſtreets of the Citie, euen how manie tiles are vpon the houſes, to ſo manie perils art thou ſubiect: If there bee an Iron toole in thy hand or thy friends, the harme is readie prepared: how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie wilde beaſts thou ſeeſt, they are all armed to thy deſtruction. If thou mean
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2670:21"/>to ſhut vppe thy ſelfe in a garden, well ſenced, where may appeare nothing but pleaſantneſſe of aire and ground, there ſometime lurketh a Serpent:</q> The houſe which is ſubiect to windes and ſtormes, doth continually threaten thee with falling on thy head, I ſpeake not of poyſonings, treaſons, robberies, open vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, of which part do beſiege vs at home, and part doe follow vs abroad, examples tending to this purpoſe are infinite, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I will produce a few, thereby to put vs in minde that the ſame things may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto our ſelues, for which cauſe hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhould a moment of our life time bee ſpent, without due and intire conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our death. If then we aſcend the theater of mans life, and looke about, we ſhall ſee ſome to haue periſhed with ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den death
<note n="1" place="margin">Ananias &amp; Sap.</note>, others with griefe
<note n="2" place="margin">Eli.</note>, others w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ioy
<note n="3" place="margin">Rhodius Diagoras.</note>, others with gluttony
<note n="4" place="margin">Domit. Afer.</note>, others with drunkenneſſe
<note n="5" place="margin">At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tila King of Hunnes.</note>, others with hunger
<note n="6" place="margin">Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes.</note>, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with thirſt
<note n="7" place="margin">Thales mileſius.</note>, others in their laſciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dalliances
<note n="8" place="margin">Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iius Gal.</note>, others with ouerwatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<note n="9" place="margin">M. Atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius.</note>, others with poyſon
<note n="10" place="margin">Phocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Henric. 7. Emp. in a feaſt by a Mounke.</note>: ſome by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2670:21"/>fire from heauen
<note n="11" place="margin">The So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtatius the Emperour an Euty chia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>haer.</note>, ſome by waters
<note n="12" place="margin">M. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus.</note>, ſome by earthquakes
<note n="13" place="margin">E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phraſius biſh of Antioch.</note>, ſome ſwallowed vp quicke
<note n="14" place="margin">Coran, Dathan and Abiron.</note>, ſome ſtifled with ſmoake and vapours
<note n="15" place="margin">Catulus.</note>, ſome choaked with flies
<note n="16" place="margin">Adrian the Pope, 1159.</note>, ſome with a fall, &amp; ſliding off their foot
<note n="17" place="margin">Neſtorius the haer.</note>, ſome at the disburdening of nature
<note n="18" place="margin">Arrius haer.</note>, ſome vvith a ſuddaine fall from their horſe
<note n="19" place="margin">Philip K. of France. Iudge Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil of Tane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtock in Deuo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note>, others killed and torne aſunder by Dogs
<note n="20" place="margin">Heraclitus Lucian the Apoſt.</note>, Horſes
<note n="21" place="margin">Hippolitus</note>, Lions
<note n="22" place="margin">Licus Em.</note>, Beares
<note n="23" place="margin">40. Child.</note>, Boares
<note n="24" place="margin">Ancaeus K. of Samos.</note>, Rats
<note n="25" place="margin">Hato biſh. of Menas. Trag. 3. act 1.</note>, and the like. I forbeare to ſpeake of other ſtrange and vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate deaths, as that of <hi>Milo</hi> Crotoniates by the ſtocke of an Oake which he had deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to teare aſunder, but his ſtrength fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, and the clift ſuddenly cloſing, was ſo faſt held by the hands, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a prey to the beaſts of the field. And that of Poet <hi>Aeſchylus,</hi> who vncouering his bald pate in the warme ſunne, had his brain pan broken by the blow of a <hi>Tortuiſe,</hi> which an Eagle, taking his head for a white Marble ſtone, let fall to breake, that afterward ſhe might deuoure it. And that of <hi>Charles</hi> King of Nauarre, who for the curing of ſome aches, hauing his bodie
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2670:22"/>wrapped about with a linnen cloth, that firſt, had beene well ſteeped in <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> was ſuddenly and vnfortunately burnt by a candle, which his Phyſician hauing ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the cloath about him, and wanting a knife to cut the thred, tooke to burne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, and the thred flaming to the cloth, caught ſuch a ſuddaine hold of the ſame, and <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> that before any meanes could bee applied, the King in this flame vvas burnt to death. I ſpeake nothing of others who haue vntimely periſhed: ſome by one meanes, ſome by another. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all with that ſaying of * <hi>Seneca, Eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere vitam nemo non homini poteſt, at nemo mortem, mille ad hanc aditus patent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay then? doe ſo manie things vvithin vs, ſo many things vvithout vs, ſo manie things about vs, threaten a continuall death vnto vs? <hi>Miſer homo cur te ad mortem non componis, cum ſis pro certo mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus,</hi> Then vvretched man thou art, that doeſt not prepare thy ſelfe for death, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou muſt certainely die.</p>
            <p>But alas the diuell doth ſo deafe vs, the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2670:22"/>world doth ſo blind vs, and the ſenſualitie of the fleſh maketh vs ſo extreamely ſenceleſſe, that we neither heare, nor ſee, nor feele what is euerie minute likely to befall vs. If wee be young, wee feare not death at our backes, if old, wee looke a ſquint and ſee not death before our eyes. But hearken O young man and learne, as the old man can not liue long, ſo the young man may die quickly: certaine it is thou ſhalt die, vncertaine when, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auſe thou ſhouldeſt alwaies liue readie to die. But if it were ſo that in thy youth thou hadſt a leaſe of thy life till age, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Father of heauen, ratified by his Sonne, and ſealed vnto thee by the whole Trinitie, then perchance there might be ſome pretence of thy careleſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But now ſeeing euery houre may be the laſt vnto thee, ſince euerie moment may diſſolue this earthly Tabernacle, ſince a thouſand chances may at all times take thee vnawares, and bereaue thee of thy ſoule: who but more then mad would not conſider of his end, and follow the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2670:23"/>Prophet <hi>Eſaies</hi> counſell, to ſeeke the Lord in time, and <hi>Salomons</hi> precept, to learne wiſedome in his youth.</p>
            <p>In like manner the olde man, hee will not thinke of death, vntill the time of his death, thinking to become a ſudden Saint, who hath all his life time liued a wicked worldling. But hearken thou old man, and learne by the rich man in the Goſpell, ſo he had alſo caſt vp his reſt, hee was ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led rich and ioyfull, and deferred to bee godly till he ſaw occaſion, but what ſaith the Spirit of God: <hi>O foole this night ſhall they take thy ſoule from thee,</hi> this night in middeſt of thy ioylitie, in the ſecuritie of thy ſleepe, ſuddenly, vnwittingly ſhalt thou die. O miſerable caſe (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſten</hi>) when ſuddenly the ſenſes faile, the bodie languiſheth, death readie to burſt in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the heart ſtrings, the conſcience hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie with ſinne, the diuell readie to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thee. Who in this plight would not value a minute of repentance, to a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of wealth, and yet we baniſh away, daies, and moneths, and yeeres, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2670:23"/>the caſualtie in the end. I vviſh therefore, that old men as they haue a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge of yeeres, ſo alſo they had the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge of foreſight heerein; that as they ſee their bodies bending towardes the earth, ſo they learne to ſend their ſoules towards heauen, and if they ſhould not vviſh for their diſſolution with <hi>Paul,</hi> yet they ſhould wait all the daies of their life for their changing with <hi>Iob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, all men almoſt, both young and olde, rich and poore, of all faſhions, and of all degrees, put off this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of death, and neuer thinke or prepare to die, till they finde and feele they can no longer liue. But, O let me beſeech you all that heere mee this day, to exempt your ſelues from this ſupine and oxe like ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. You know for certaine you muſt die, you are euerie moment ſubiect vnto death, a thouſand thouſand chances maie euerie daie bereaue you of your life? why then eſteeme of euerie preſent daie, as the daie of your death, and make ſuch conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of all your waies, words and works,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2670:24"/>as if you were preſently to giue an account of your life. <hi>Qui conſiderat qualiter erit in morte pauidus &amp; prouidus erit in operatione,</hi> He that thinkes alwaies of dying will bee cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in his doing.</p>
            <p>Thinke therefore, O thinke, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke your ſelues of this, and in the depth of theſe thoughts, prepare your ſelues for death. Set your houſes, yea ſet your hearts in order, call your ſoules to account, turne your ſelues as
<note n="*" place="margin">2. Kin. 20</note> 
               <hi>Ezechias</hi> did to the wall, that is, from the world to God; weepe, weepe, and bewaile your ſinnes paſt, keepe a narrow watch ouer your heart for the time to come,
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſa. 38.</note> praie with <hi>Dauid, Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not the ſinnes of my youth,</hi> and with Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> Lord forgiue me my faults here, where I haue ſinned, for elſe where I cannot be relieued, except I haue my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don heere; It is in vaine to expect the reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full comfort of forgiueneſſe heereafter.
<note n="*" place="margin">2. cor. 6.2</note> Now is the acceptable time, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, now is the daie of ſaluation: This world is for thy repentance, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for thy recompence, <hi>Hic locus luctae,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2670:24"/>ille coronae, hoc cunaeorum tempus eſt illud coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natorum,</hi> as Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaketh, This is the place and time of combating, that of crowning, this of working, that of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding, this for thy mourning, that for thy comforting Now God is helping vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all men, ſeeke yee therefore the
<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 55.</note> Lord whiles he is neere, and poſt not off till to morrow, for you know not what a daie maie bring forth. It is certaine death will come, but it commeth for the moſt part like a theefe ſtealing, and creeping with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any warning, take heede you bee not taken vnawares. You ſee the ſtroke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is vniuerſall, for if the reuerence of old age, could haue diſcountenanced it, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſhaleth</hi> had not died. If ſtrength of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die could haue reſiſted it, <hi>Sampſon</hi> had not died. If maieſtie could haue terrified it, if counſel could haue perſwaded it, if riches could haue bribed it: Nor <hi>Solomon,</hi> nor <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel,</hi> nor <hi>Diues</hi> had died. But <hi>Methu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaleth</hi> is dead, and <hi>Samſon</hi> is dead, and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> and <hi>Achitophel,</hi> and <hi>Diues</hi> are dead, and what is it can free a man from death?
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2670:25"/>Nay, if youth, if beautie, if vertue, if pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, could worke any relent in death, from embracing his cruell hands in mortall bloud: ſee where youth, where beautie, where vertue, where pietie lye enſhrined, whollie now defaced, obſcured, eclipſed, and ouerſhadowed in death. O death, how irrelenting is thy heart! how bloudy are thy hands! how vnpartiall is thy ſtroake! how generall is thy arreſt! oh that the liuing would conſider this. And let this ſuffice, to be ſpoken of the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalitie of deaths ſtroake. <hi>Then Sara died.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Abraham came to mourne for Sarah and to weepe for her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether <hi>Sara</hi> died in abſence of <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> is here ſaid to come to mourn for her, as the Iewes affirm ſhe did, &amp; to this end faine, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> was on mount Moriah to ſacrifice his ſonne <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the diuell to make it a reall tragedie, repreſented the manner of <hi>Iſaacs</hi> offering vp vnto <hi>Sarah,</hi> wherevpon, ſay they, ſhee tooke a conceit and died: and ſo <hi>Abraham</hi> returning from the mount, and finding
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2670:25"/>his vvife dead, is ſaid to come to mourne and to weepe for her. But <hi>Ioſephus</hi> hath ſufficiently refuted this fancie: For, if <hi>Iſaac</hi> were 25. yeeres old at the time he ſhould haue beene ſacrificed, and <hi>Sarah</hi> after that liued 12. yeeres, how then died <hi>Sarah</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentlie, when ſhe heard from the diuel her ſonne was ſacrificed. Or whether hee came from burying his father <hi>Therah,</hi> as ſome thinke, whom the Ieſuite <hi>Pererius</hi> would haue to die but two yeeres before, but the truth is that hee was dead 62. yeeres before, for <hi>Abraham</hi> was now 137. yeeres olde, who vvas borne in the 70. yeere of <hi>Therahs</hi> age, who liued 205. yeeres in all: ſo <hi>Abraham</hi> was 75. yeeres old, when his father died, to that adde 62. ſo ſhall wee haue <hi>Abrahams</hi> age of 137.
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 12.5</note>
            </p>
            <p>Or whether he be ſaid to come becauſe he went out of his tent, and entred into <hi>Sarahs</hi> tent, which is moſt probable: for though they ſoiourned together, yet their tents were aſunder, as appeareth out of the laſt verſe of the 24. Chapter, as the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2670:26"/>manner of thoſe Countries was, the men to haue their tents by themſelues apart, and the women their tents apart, as heere, among whom we ſoiourne: vve ſee at this daie the Turkes haue their houſes and their roomes apart, halfe for themſelues, and the other halfe for their wiues and women ſlaues: or howſoeuer it was, wee will not ſo much inquire from whence he came, as the end of his comming: which was to mourne and weep for <hi>Sara,</hi> whence we obſerue.</p>
            <p>That naturall affection is commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all: In <hi>Abraham,</hi> therefore in others, and that not euerie light touch of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but a mourning and weeping, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affection, and an outward action, ſorrow within, and ſadneſſe without, the hearts griefe, and the eie teares muſt goe together. For weeping and teares with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, are tokens of loue within. As the Iewes gather from the teares of Chriſt, which he ſhedde for the death of <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 11.</note> Behold how he loued him, how appeares that, euen from this, And Ieſus wept, for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2670:26"/>then ſaid the Iewes, vvhen they ſaw him vveepe, Behold how he loued him.</p>
            <p>Where loue is, teares are, if extremity of griefe ſuppreſs not the paſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of loue. And therefore, God hath made men as liuing, ſo louing creatures, to the end that they ſhould not be as ſtockes and ſtones <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſenſeleſſe and void of affection, but that liuing and louing together, the loue of the one ſhould not end vvith the life of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but in token that he loued while hee liued, the ſuruiuer ſhould accompanie the dead to the graue vvith his teares, and weepe that they two can no longer liue and loue together.</p>
            <p>Therefore the cuſtome of ſome nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to vveepe at their childrens birth, and to laugh at their death, I hold vnnaturall: for verie nature it ſelfe (as alſo <hi>Euripides</hi> a meere naturaliſt could tell vs) ſeemeth to haue ingraffed &amp; inacted this deſire into euery one: yea though he dye (for ſome foule offence) a ſhamefull death, to haue yet his kinred &amp; his frends to celebrate his funerall, with their teares and lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2670:27"/>and the ſaying of <hi>Solon</hi> vvas more na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and humane:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mors mea ne careat lachrymis, linquamus amicis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Maerorem, vt celebrent funera cum gemitu.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Then that proud and ambitious vaunt of <hi>Ennius,</hi> which yet <hi>Tully</hi> much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nemo me lachrymis decoret, nec funera fletu,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faxit, cur! volito viua per ora virûm.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>It is all one as if he had ſaid, Let no man loue me: for where loue is griefe will ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be, if the thing beloued be taken away. And therfore <hi>Abraham</hi> wept for <hi>Sara</hi> here, and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and his brethren wept for their father <hi>Iacob,</hi> and <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren wept for <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> Thus the Iſraelites wept for <hi>Aaron,</hi> &amp; <hi>Moſes</hi> for <hi>Samuel:</hi> thus all Iuda and Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lem mourned, and made ſorrowfull ſongs and lamentations for <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> and <hi>Ieremiah</hi> the Prophet himſelfe lamented <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> and all ſinging men and women mourned for <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> and behold this is written in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations. Thus the Diſciples wept for <hi>Stephen,</hi> thus <hi>Marie</hi> and <hi>Martha</hi> wept for <hi>Lazarus,</hi> thus others though neuer ſo god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2670:27"/>neuer ſo learned, neuer ſo wiſe, haue wept, neither could they forbeare, <hi>nempe homines,</hi> for they are men, and to weepe is humane, M. <hi>Antonius</hi> the Emperour wee finde vvas a wiſe man, his ſurname was <hi>Philoſophus</hi> the Philoſopher, and yet hee could not refraine to lament and weepe bitterly at the death of his Tutor, which when ſome reprehended in him, as vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming both the maieſtie of an Emperor, and grauitie of a Philoſopher, <hi>Antonius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> excuſing him, ſaid vnto them, <hi>Sinite vt homo ſit, neque enim imperium, aut Philoſophia, hominem ex homine tollit, neque humanis ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; affectibus hominem exuit:</hi> Let him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone hee doth but his owne, for neither Soueraignetie nor Philoſophie, can take from him the nature of a man, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt him from humane paſsions and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. In likewiſe
<note n="*" place="margin">26. Serm. in Cant.</note> Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> we all know was a holy and deuout man, yet hee could not but weepe for his brother <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rardus,</hi> and yeelds the reaſon: For if one Oxe, ſaith he, finding another Oxe dead, low and roare for it, and in his kinde cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2670:28"/>a funerall for the dead: what ſhould man doe for man, whom reaſon teacheth and affection draweth? Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> alſo was a graue godly man, and yet he weeps for his dead brother, and why not, ſaith he, <hi>bos bouem requirit?</hi> doth one Oxe low for another if hee want his mate with whom he was wont to be coupled? <hi>Et ego te frater non requiram,</hi> and ſhall not I deſire thee againe my brother? ſhall not I weep for thee, ſhall I euer forget thee with whom I haue liued ſo long? No, no, my brother I will remember thee, I will ſhed teares for thee, and let no man condemne me; for if we ſhed ſome few teares, which runne ſoftly like the waters of Siloh, no force, <hi>Erunt non doloris ilices ſed indices amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> they will not bewray in vs any want of faith, but onely teſtifie an aboundance of loue. Therefore the Wiſe-man exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs, ſaying; <hi>My ſonne powre forth teares o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the dead, and begin to mourne as if thou hadſt ſuffered great harme thy ſelfe:</hi> and then couer his bodie, according to his appointment, and neglect not his buriall, make a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2670:28"/>lamentation,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ecc. 28.16</note> and bee earneſt in mourning, and vſe lamentation as hee is worthy, and that a day or two leaſt thou be euill ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>But here by the way let vs obſerue and learne, that if we may not bee ſenſeleſſe as Stoicks, but ought to mourne and weepe for thoſe that die a corporall death, what are we to doe! how are we to grieue! what teares ſhould wee powre forth? for thoſe that die a ſpirituall death? ſo
<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 15.</note> as did the prodigall ſonne, ſo as did many of the Corinthians whom
<note n="*" place="margin">2. Cor. 12 21.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> bewailed, ſo as did thoſe pleaſure-mungers, who though they liued, yet as the
<note n="*" place="margin">Tim. 5.6.</note> Apoſtle ſaith, were dead. So as do too many among vs, who neither regard the word of God, which is the life of our ſoules, nor our own ſoules, vvhich are the life of our ſelues. Oh that my head vvere full of water, and mine eies a fountaine of teares, that I might weepe day and night for this ſupine, fooliſh, and retchleſſe ſecuritie
<note n="*" place="margin">Ecc. 22.12</note> 
               <hi>Seuen dayes</hi> ſaith the Wiſe-man, <hi>doe men mourne for him that is dead, but the lamentation for the foole and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2670:29"/>ſhould indure all the dayes of their life:</hi> and why for the dead, he is at reſt, but the life of the foole and the vngodly is vvorſe then death. Let vs therefore doe that ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> for our ſoules, which wee doe for mens bodies, let vs bewaile the loſſe of our ſaluation, and let vs lament the death of our ſoules: for greater is the loſſe, ſaith Saint <hi>Auſten,</hi> of one ſoule, then of a thouſand bodies. In ſo much that the vvhole world, ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> is not of value enough for the price of one ſoule. But who is more dead, ſaith he, then him that carrieth fire in his boſome, ſin in his ſoule, and neither feeles it, nor feares it, nor flies from it? And ſuch is euery vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man: for him therefore, whether it bee our ſelues or others, vvee are ſpecially to mourne and vveepe.</p>
            <p>And yet in both theſe, there is a golden meane, vvhich vvee muſt warily obſerue and keepe, to vvit, a meane in vveeping for our ſinnes, and a meane in vveeping for our friends; in weeping for our ſinnes, that wee weepe in faith and not deſpaire, in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2670:29"/>vveeping for our frends, that vvee vveepe in loue and not as without hope. <hi>Elegant,</hi> to which purpoſe are thoſe verſes of his, vvhoſoeuer vvere the author.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Deflendi ſunt mortui, ſed temperant ius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nam mortui non ſunt, eandem ſed viam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quam cogit omnes ingredi neceſsitas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Praemuniere nobis, nos in poſterum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Idem ſequemur ipſos in confortium,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Communis &amp; vita fruemur patriae.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> Which will vs to weepe for the dead, but yet to obſerue a meaſure in weeping, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe dead they are, not whom wee call dead; but onely gone before vs the way vnto eternall life, which wee muſt follow after. The Prophet <hi>Abraham</hi> kept this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in weeping for <hi>Sarah</hi> here: for when he had wept and mourned for her, <hi>(i.)</hi> when hee thought he had wept enough; then he aroſe from the ſight of his corps, <hi>(i.)</hi> hee left weeping for her bodie, and tooke care for her buriall: hee was not ſenſeleſſe at her death, for hee did that for her, which he did not when he was to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice his owne and onely ſonne <hi>Iſaac:</hi> he
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2670:30"/>wept for her, he vvept not for him, but he kept a meane in his weeping, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he roſe vp and vvent away from her wherein hee ſhewed himſelfe not void of affection, but obſeruant of a moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and this <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is it which the Lord commendeth, and it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which the Apoſtle condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>I would not brethren,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>haue you ignorant concerning them which are aſleepe, that yee ſorrow not euen as other which haue no hope:</hi> How did other ſorrow? euen exceſsiuely, vnmeaſurably, immoderately; without meane, meaſure, or moderation? Some cutting and ſlaſhing their faces, ſome ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and tearing their lockes, their beards, their haire, their attire; ſome ſhauing their heads, in token of ſorrow: ſo did the
<note n="*" place="margin">Alex. ab. Alex. lib. 3. cap. 7.</note> Egyptians, Amorites, Mileſians and Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: and do not our owne eies witnes the ſame in the Greekes, at euerie ſolemne fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall? how do the ſilly women diſhiuer their golden traces? how doe they diſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure their amiable faces? vvhat buffets do they giue their gentle breaſts? what piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2670:30"/>ſhriekings? what hideous howlings? what heart bleeding ſobs? vvhat bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing ſighs doe they vtter? and all for outward manifeſtation, of their inward contriſtation: and this exceſsiue, vnmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furable, immoderate lamentation the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle condemneth; and good reaſons there are why wee ſhould not ſorrow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond a meaſure whereof the firſt may bee.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Diuina voluntas</hi> the diuine vvill, vnto vvhich humane vvill muſt ſubmit and conforme it ſelfe. Now nothing is done vvithout the diuine vvill, vvithout it a
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> Sparrow falleth not to the ground, much leſſe a man: vvhy then O baſe man, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou ſtriue againſt the pleaſure of the moſt high God?
<note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 41.</note> vvhy rather ſaieſt thou not vvith Chriſt, Not as I vvill, but as thou vvilt my Father. Hath a maſter power of his ſeruant, ſaith Saint
<note n="*" place="margin">De fide reſur.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> to lead him vvhether hee vvill? and hath not God ouer man? <hi>Placeat ergo homini,</hi> ſaith the Heathen
<note n="*" place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Lucullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Seneca, quicquid Deo placet,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let man be pleaſed with the diuine wil and pleaſure, and thus reſolue vvith him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2670:31"/>that God alwaies calleth him out of this life when he is at his beſt, if he be good that he turne not euill; if euill, that he wax not worſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Diuina aequitas,</hi> diuine right and equity; it is reaſon and equity that what is receiued vpon bare lending ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored at demanding,
<note n="*" place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> as the holy man <hi>Iob</hi> confeſſed. It is lawfull for euery one to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire his owne; now, all that we haue, our very life and being is not our owne,
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 100</note> but Gods: he made vs, and not we our ſelues, hee may with good equity recall vs when hee pleaſeth. Wee ſee how patiently the greateſt Baſha, either in Port or abroad, yeeldeth his necke to the Bow-ſtring at the hatmaum and command of his King, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be right or wrong; for why (ſayth he) I am his ſlaue, my life was long agoe at his diſpoſe; it is through his clemencie that I liued vntill now. And ſhall wee be leſſe obedient vnto our good God, whoſe ſlaues we are, whoſe call is euer iuſt? Nay, rather let vs be thankefull vnto him that he hath lent vs our life ſo long. So was Saint
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2670:31"/>
               <hi>Bernard,</hi> who after his mourning for his brother <hi>Satirus,</hi> comforts himſelfe, and breaketh forth into this acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Ingratus diuinitati eſſe non poſſum,</hi> I may not be vnthankefull to the diuine Maieſty, I am rather to reioyce that I had ſuch a brother, then to ſorrow that I loſt him, for that was but a gift, this was a debt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Fraterna vtilitas,</hi> the benefit of the departed, for from how many euils is he freed that dyeth in the
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 7. Phil. 1. Apoc. 14.</note> Lord? How great the benefit is, Chriſt ſheweth, where he ſaith, if you
<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 14</note> loued me you would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce becauſe I go to my Father: and if we loue our friend indeed, vve vvould rather reioyce then too much grieue at his death, for hee is departed from vs, he is gone out of the vvorld, hee hath left the earth; but hee is gone vnto Chriſt, he is entred the Citie of God, the celeſtiall Ieruſalem; <hi>Non ergo amiſsi ſed praemiſsi,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fulgentius,</hi> therefore the godly deceaſed are not loſt foreuer, but left for a time, not gone away finally from vs, but onely gone to God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:2670:32"/>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Fletus inutilitas,</hi> the vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes of exceſsiue weeping, for as a moth the garment, a worme the wood, ſo too much ſorrow hurteth the heart;
<note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 25.</note> therefore the wiſe man as hee exhorteth to weepe for the dead; ſo he counſelleth to comfort our ſelues againe for our heauineſſe, for of heauineſſe commeth death, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the heart breaketh the ſtrength.
<note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 18.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt is, <hi>Reſurrectio generalis,</hi> the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Reſurection, we put not off our appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſaith <hi>Lud. Viues,</hi> vnwillingly becauſe we thinke to put them on againe; ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let vs be vnwilling to lay aſide our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die which after a while we ſhall reſume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. And as we greiue not at the ſetting of the Sunne, becauſe we know it will riſe againe. So let vs not ſorrow at the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a ſoule, which vvee knovv vvill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe. For vvhy (ſaith
<note n="*" place="margin">Tertul in lib. de pati.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi>) ſhouldeſt thou too impatiently greiue at the departure of him vvith-vvhome thou beleeueſt ſhortly to meete againe! Hee is not to bee lamented, vvho is gone before, hee is onely vvanted for a time, and his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2670:32"/>want is vvith patience to bee borne. <hi>Cur enim immoderatè feras abijſſe quem mox ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queris?</hi> For why ſhouldeſt thou immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately lament his abſence, whom thou thy ſelfe muſt ſoone follow after? and all of vs ſhall ſurely meet againe at the generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. We may indeed, ſaith <hi>S. Ierome,</hi> wiſh for them, becauſe we want them, but wee muſt not weepe out of meaſure for them, becauſe they are with God. Loue I grant compells vs to weepe, but faith for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids vs to weepe immoderately, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Paulinus</hi> ſaith, that we may, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding our faith, performe to the dead the duties of loue; yet we muſt firſt, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the duties of loue, afford to our ſelues the comforts of faith. And thus <hi>Abraham</hi> wept for <hi>Sarah</hi> here, loue inforced him to weepe, but faith reſtrained him from exceeding the bounds of moderate lamentation.</p>
            <p>You ſee then that wee are to weepe for the death of our godly friends de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, but withall you ſee how ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe wee ought to bee in weepinge,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2670:33"/>conſidering our good hope that are aliue, and their good hap that are dead. And this that dead bodie, or rather that <hi>Cadauer,</hi> that <hi>Caro data vermibus,</hi> for her fleſh and bones by this time are turned into duſt and aſhes, which is the preſent ſpectacle &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of our eyes, &amp; which ſome of you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps euen at this inſtant, ſo ſeriouſly think of, others ſo much lament for. If it, I ſay, ſhould receiue againe her ſoule, vntie her winding knots, breake through her Coffin, &amp; ſtand vp before you, ſhe would preach &amp; ſay the ſame vnto you; weepe, if you pleaſe, for my departure, for this ſhall be a token of your affection; but weepe not too im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderately, for this will argue your indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion: for know, that though I be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, yet I am not periſhed, but am ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perfected. I am now in the ſtate of perfection, where I feele no infirmitie, where I am not tempted vnto ſinne, but ſing a continuall Halleluiah to the Lord. I am now where I behold the glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of the Trinity, where I looke on the amiable countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of my Sauiour, where
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2670:33"/>I enioy the ſweet ſociety of Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, where I haue ſaciety without loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe; loue, without hatred; peace, without diſcord; ioy, without ſorrow; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall bliſſe, without ende or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion: and therefore ſpare teares for mee, weepe not too much, for the more you weepe, the more you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet and diſturbe me. This would the ſoule of this dead body ſay, if it ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe: but ſhe is paſt ſpeaking, and her ſoule returning, vntill the generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of all. Wee will therefore leaue her to her happineſſe, and paſſe to the third ſubiect of our ſad diſcourſe, which is, the Lot of humane Life; and that is a pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage on earth. <hi>The life of man is a pilgrimage on earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Man may be ſaid to be a ſtranger and a pilgrime on earth, either in reſpect of his ſoule, which is not of the earth, but by diuine infuſion; or in reſpect of the whole man, which was ſometime the Citizen of Paradiſe, but now a vvanderer vpon the face of the vvhole earth; or moſt properly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2670:34"/>in reſpect of the heauenly <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> from vvhence, as alſo from the Lord, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full here on earth (vvhoſe conuerſation is in
<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> Heauen) are ſtrangers as long as they are in the
<note n="*" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> body. Whence Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> inferreth, <hi>Omnis homo est aduena naſcendo, &amp; incola viuendo, quia compellitur migrare morien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do:</hi> Euery man is a forreiner by birth, and a ſtranger by life, becauſe he is compelled to depart hence by death. Therefore ſaid <hi>Abraham</hi> vnto the <hi>Hittites,</hi> I am a ſtranger and a forreiner among you; among them! yea, on the vvhole earth, for his vvhole life was a pilgrimage on earth, as his gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dchild <hi>Iacob</hi> calleth both it and his ovvne; The vvhole courſe of my pilgrimage (ſayth hee vnto <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) is an hundred and thirtie yeares, few and euill haue the daies of my life beene, and I haue not attained vnto the yeares of the life of my fathers, in the daies of their pilgrimage.
<note place="margin">Gen. 47. Heb. 11. verſ. 13.</note> And <hi>Paul,</hi> bringing in a whole Catalogue of pilgrimes in the elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth to the <hi>Hebrewes, Abel, Enoch, Noah, Abraham,</hi> and the reſt, at length concludeth of all; All theſe died in faith, and confeſſed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2670:34"/>that they were ſtrangers and pilgrimes on the earth, vpon which Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerreth, <hi>Ipſe eſt Chriſtianus,</hi> he alone is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, that in his owne houſe, and in his owne Countrie, acknowledgeth himſelfe to be a pilgrime. Our Countrie is aboue, there we ſhall be no ſtrangers, but here e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie man is a ſtranger, euen in his owne houſe. Let no man deceiue himſelfe, he is a ſtranger, <hi>Velit nolit hoſpes eſt,</hi> whether hee will or no he is a ſtranger. Now if this were the lot of Gods deareſt children in olde time, we may not looke for a permanent Citie here.</p>
            <p>We ſee then where we muſt make the beginning of all godlineſſe, euen in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this world, and acknowledging our ſelues to bee but pilgrimes in the ſame Conſider, ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai 51.2.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> your father, and <hi>Sarah</hi> that bare you; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that <hi>Abraham</hi> was a ſtranger and a pilgrim on earth, he had not ſo much land where he liued as might ſuffice for the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of his dead, for in hope of future things he deſpiſed the preſent, and in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2670:35"/>expectation of greater good in the life to come, he little reckoned the good of this preſent life, a ſhame to vs that liue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grace, if we come ſhort of him that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued before the law. You would thinke him an vntoward ſonne, that being ſent by his father into forraigne Countries, with this charge, to learne the tongues, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the manners, and to hearken after the ſtate of the Land, and be prouided alwaies to returne when hee ſhall call him backe; yet notwithſtanding being out of ſight playes out of mind, and ſits downe, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſurfets vpon the diuerſitie of pleaſures, is inamoured with the beauty of <hi>Italie,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with the pride of <hi>Spaine, Fraunce</hi> muſt fit him with fine ſtuffes, <hi>England</hi> muſt fit him with new faſhions, <hi>India</hi> muſt guilt him with gold, <hi>Arabia</hi> perfume him with ſweet ſmels, as though the world were made to be his minion, but leaſt of any is his Father remembred, and worſt of all is his charge of obſeruancy performed, what other then can we thinke of our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, whome God our heauenly father
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2670:35"/>hath ſet abroad in this world, as in a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Countrie to obſerue the Heauens, which is the Booke, and the ſtarres which are ſo many golden Characters of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, to view the earth which is a large ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the ornaments thereof ſo many footeſteps of his power; and out of all theſe to learne vnto our ſelues, that we may be able to declare vnto others the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, and in the end to be willing to returne vnto him againe vvhen he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth. Yet for all this vve can no ſooner be out of kenning, but out of caring too, and euen glut our ſelues vvith vvorldly vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as if earth, not heauen vvere our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall home. This my beloued is a great negligence, a madneſſe, a fooliſh frenzie, I know not vvhat to call it, but euen a lul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our ſelues aſleepe in the cradle of this vvorlds ſecuritie.</p>
            <p>Againe, if vvee bee pilgrimes heere on earth, vve muſt learne to doe as pilgrimes doe. <hi>Quis non,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Cyprian, peregrè conſtitutus properet in patriam regredi,</hi> What pilgrime doth not make ſpeed to returne
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2670:36"/>home into his owne Countrey, vvho haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſaile homewards, doth not wiſh for a proſperous winde, that hee may ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily imbrace his long deſired friends and parents? and vvhat are vvee but pilgrimes on earth? vvhat is our countrey, but Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe? vvho are our parents? but the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches? vvhy make vvee not haſt? vvhy runne vve not vnto them, that wee may ſee our countrey, ſalute our parents? an infinite number of acquaintance expect vs there: our parents, our brethren and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, our children, our kindred, our friends, that are alreadie ſecure of their owne immortalitie, but yet ſollicitous for our ſafetie, what ioy, what comfort will it be to ſee, to imbrace them. What celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all pleaſures are there without all feare of dying? and with certaine eternitie of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing? there is the glorious quire of the Angels, the exultant number of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the bleſſed company of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, the crowned troupe of Martyrs, the triumphant ſocietie of the Saints: who whiles they liued here as out of their own
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2670:36"/>countrey were contemned; no men more, but are now heires to a crowne, and ſit vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a throne bleſſed for euer.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, are wee pilgrimes on earth? Let me beſeech you then beloued as the
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.11.</note> Apoſtle beſought his beloued, <hi>Dearely beloued I beſeech you as ſtrangers and pilgrimes, abſtaine from fleſhly luſts which fight againſt the ſoule.</hi> For a pilgrime will keepe on ſtill the Kings high way, and neuer turne to by paths: if he ſees ſome quarrelling hee ſtaies not to hearken to them; if he meet a wedding, hee turnes not to accompany them: but keepes on his way ſtill becauſe he is a pilgrime, <hi>Ad patriam ſuſpirat, ad patria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tendit,</hi> he ſigheth after his owne countrey, and haſteneth vnto his owne home, hee carrieth nothing but his food and his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, he will not trouble himſelfe with any other burthen, <hi>Retinet quod alimentum, reijcit quod impedimentum,</hi> hee vouchſafeth onely ſaith <hi>Plurarch,</hi> to carrie his food, but caſteth off al other things as hindra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. Let the voluptuous man who turneth aſide out of the way vnto dalliance, let the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2670:37"/>man, who hath euer a great ſacke at his backe remember this.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if wee bee pilgrimes heere on earth, we haue but few friends and many foes, let vs be then carefull to procure God to be our friend, ſo aſſure we our ſelues, our enemies though they hate vs, ſhall neuer haue the power to hurt vs, our God whom we ſerue will protect vs.</p>
            <p>And now from this ſubiect of pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, let me lead you to the home of pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes, and the houſe of death; this is the graue, which as it is the end of all our pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, ſo ſhall it be the period and end of my diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Abraham ſaid, giue me a poſſeſsion of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall with you, that I may bury my dead out of my ſight.</hi> Whence obſerue,</p>
            <p>That the bodies of the dead are to be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly buried, and honored with a graue. The iniunction hereof by God himſelfe, was as ancient within a little as <hi>Adam:</hi> for euen in Paradiſe, preſently vpon the fall, the Lord ſaid vnto him, <hi>From earth wert thou taken, and into earth ſhalt thou returne againe.</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:2670:37"/>And the God of nature ſeemeth to haue impreſſed this ſence in all the liuing, for buriall of the dead, thereby teſtifying their hope of the future reſurrection and life. For the burying of bodies is like the ſowing of ſeed, which men commit to the earth, but with certaine hope that after it is once corrupted it will riſe againe. And therefore buriall among moſt men (I ſpeake not of Canibals nor Antropopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi: vvho are rather beaſts then men, for their guts are their graue) hath euer beene ſolemnly and religiouſly practiſed.</p>
            <p>True it is if we looke into the volumes of old heatheniſh Philoſophers, and read ſongs of Poets, wee ſhall finde that they generally contemned the reſpect of buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Among Philoſophers looke vpon <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes</hi> the Cynicke, that bad his dead body ſhould be caſt to the dogs &amp; fowles of the aire, and being anſwered by his friends, that ſo it ſhould be rent and torne; hee in ſcoffe, why then ſet a ſtaffe by mee and I will beat them away with it: tuſh (ſay they) you your ſelfe ſhall bee ſenſeleſſe:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2670:38"/>why then, quoth hee, vvhat need I feare tearing? of his humour was <hi>Memppus</hi> and moſt of the Cynicks. <hi>Tullie</hi> in his queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>Tuſculane,</hi> recordeth this anſwere of <hi>Theodorus</hi> of <hi>Cyrene</hi> vnto <hi>Lyſimachus,</hi> that threatned him the croſſe. Let thy Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers feare that, ſaid he, but as for me I care not whether I rot in the ayre, or in the earth: ſo alſo ſaid <hi>Socrates in Platoes</hi> Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue called <hi>Phaedo.</hi> And as for Poets, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> in his ſeuenth Booke of the Pharſalian warre, ſpeaking of the dead that Caeſar for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad ſhould be buried or burned, after hee had deliuered (as his cuſtome is) many worthy and graue ſentences concerning this matter: at length hee ſpeaketh vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> thus:</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nil agis hac ira, tabeſue cadauera ſoluat,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>An rogus haud refert, placido natura receptat Cuncta ſinu.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In this thy wrath is worthleſs, all is one</l>
                  <l>Whether by fire or putrefaction,</l>
                  <l>Their carkaſſes diſſolue, kind nature ſtil,</l>
                  <l>Takes all into her boſome.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:2670:38"/>
            <p>And a little after,</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>— <hi>Capit omnia tellus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quae genuit, caelo tegitur qui non habet vrnam.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Earths ofſpring ſtill</l>
                  <l>returnes into earths wombe,</l>
                  <l>Who wants a graue,</l>
                  <l>heauen ſerueth for his tombe.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>And ſo the declaimer in <hi>Seneca,</hi> Nature giues euerie man a graue, to the ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackt, the water wherein hee is loſt, the bodies of the crucified drop from their croſſes vnto their graues, thoſe that are burned quicke, their verie puniſhment en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tombs them. And <hi>Virgil</hi> who appoints a place in hell for the vnburied: Yet in <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes,</hi> his words ſhew how ſmall the loſſe of a graue is.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nec tumulum curo, ſepelit natura relictos.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I weigh no tombe,</l>
                  <l>nature intombes the meaneſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>And hence it is that the heathens obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quious vnto theſe Philoſophers and Poets, as vnto ſo many Prophets and Oracles, haue no more eſteemed the bodies of the dead, then of the carkaſſe of an Aſſe: but ſome of them haue throwne their dead
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2670:39"/>bodies vnto the foules of the aire, to be deuoured, as the Parthians and Iberians: others vnto dogs, as the Maſſagites and Hircanians: others vnto fiſhes, as the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophagoi and the Ichthyophagoi: others vnto men themſelues &amp; of bodies of men, haue made tombes of men, as the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Padeans, Iſſedonians, and thoſe of Scythia.</p>
            <p>Yet we Chriſtians ſhould be no imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of their barbarous inhumanitie, nor contemne and caſt away the bodies of our dead, chiefely of the righteous and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, whom the holy Ghoſt, ſaith Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten,</hi> vſed as organes and inſtruments vnto all good vvorkes. For if the Law will vs, ſaith Saint
<note n="*" place="margin">Ciuitate Dei. cap. 13. &amp; ad Paulinum. Lib. Tob. ca. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> to couer the naked: how much rather ought we to interre the dead; and if loue and kindnes moue vs to accompany our friends ſome part of the way, when they ſet forwards to trauell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to farre Countries, how much ſooner in their iourney vnto the celeſtial manſions, whence they ſhall neuer returne againe? And if the garment or ring of ones father,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2670:39"/>as Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> ſaith, bee ſo much the more eſteemed of his poſteritie, by how much they held him deere in affection, then are not our bodies to be deſpiſed, ſeeing vvee weare them more neere vnto our ſelues, then any ring or attire whatſoeuer. And therefore the funeralls of the righteous in time of old, were performed with a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous care, their funerals celebrated, and their monuments prouided, and they themſelues in their life time would lay a charge vpon their children and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, concerning the burying or tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their bodies. <hi>Iacob</hi> at his death char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged his ſonne <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> to carrie his body vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sepulcher of his Elders, and not to leaue it in
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 47</note> Egypt, and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> himſelfe commanded his brethren that they ſhould remember, and tell their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that vvhen they went away into the Land of Promiſe, they ſhould carrie his bones thither with them.
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tob. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Tobie</hi> in bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the dead well pleaſed the Lord, as the Angell teſtified. And the Lord himſelfe being to riſe againe the third day, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2670:40"/>the good worke of that religious woman,
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 26</note> 
               <hi>Marie Magdalen,</hi> who powred the precious ointment vpon his head and bodie, and did it to bury him. And the
<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 19</note> Goſpell hath crowned <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of Arima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaea, and <hi>Nicodemus</hi> with eternall praiſe, that tooke downe his bodie from the croſſe, and gaue it honeſt and honourable buriall. And what thinke you, might <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> deſerue but for burying <hi>Rachel,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> for burying <hi>Sara</hi> here.</p>
            <p>Nay the very Gentiles in old time bare ſuch reſpect and reuerence towards the dead,
<note place="margin">For at Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, our Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſh haue no buriall place allowed them but onely the Sea, nor at Zant, but are carried vp int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Morea a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong Turkes, &amp; at Ligornes and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Italie, an Engliſhman dying without Confeſſion, is throwne into ſome ditch and made a prey for the fowles.</note> that they denied not their verie ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies the honour of a burial, the humanity of <hi>Alexander</hi> vnto <hi>Darius,</hi> of <hi>Hanniball</hi> vnto <hi>Marcellus,</hi> of <hi>Caeſar</hi> vnto <hi>Pompey</hi> ſufficiently witneſſe the ſame, and at this day we our ſelues finde the like reſpect among the Turkes, though they hold vs baſe and hate vs liuing, yet (heerein more kinde then Papiſts) they neither hinder our bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, nor violate our graues, a hidden ſence and natural humanity moueth them to this, and what an vncouth thing is it
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2670:40"/>to ſee a Turke kinde, and a Chriſtian cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell. But yet theſe and the like authorities, proue not any ſence to bee in the dead carkaſſes themſelues, but ſignifie that the prouidence of God extendeth euen vnto the verie bodies of the dead (for hee is pleaſed vvith ſuch good deeds) and doe build vp the beliefe of the reſurrection. We doe not accompany or burie honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably a dead Aſſe, or a dead Oxe, becauſe they ſhall not riſe againe, but this office we performe vnto dead men to ſignifie that there is one condition of beaſts, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of men: for men ſhal riſe againe with their bodies vnto euerlaſting life, a beaſt ſhall periſh and vaniſh into nothing. To vvhich purpoſe the cuſtome vvas in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time, as <hi>Origen</hi> obſerueth, that the Prieſts and the Laiety yeerely vpon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine daies, did aſſemble at the graues and tombes of their Parents and friends, and there render thankes vnto God for the dead that had departed in faith, and pray not for the dead, nor offer any ſacrifice for them) but for the like godly and peaceable
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2670:41"/>departure vnto themſelues which was wel accepted of God.</p>
            <p>Where by the way we may learne this profitable leſſon, how great the reward of almeſdeeds done vnto the liuing may be, ſeeing this dutie and fauour ſhewed vnto the dead is not forgotten of God. And if they were worthily praiſed and bleſſed by
<note n="*" place="margin">2. Sam. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> the king, that ſhewed mercy vnto the drie bones of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ionathan,</hi> how much more praiſe ſhall they deſerue, and how ſhall they be bleſſed, that for Chriſts ſake, ſhew mercy vnto the liuing bodies of his members? they ſhall be ſure to heere the ſweet voice of their Sauiour, ſaying vnto them,
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, take the inheritance of the kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the world: for I was a hungry and yee gaue me meat, I thirſted, and yee gaue me drinke, I was a ſtranger and yee tooke mee vnto you, I was naked and yee clothed mee, I was ſicke, and yee viſited mee, I was in priſon, and yee came vnto mee: In as much as you haue done it vnto one of the leaſt of theſe my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; verily, I ſay vnto you, you haue done it
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2670:41"/>vnto mee: Come therefore, I ſay, take the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Into the inheritance of which bleſſed kingdome there is no doubt, but this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull perſon, I meane the meeke and vertuous Lady, <hi>Anne Glouer</hi> (whoſe fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall we here celebrate) is by the free mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God entred and aduanced: for why, as ſhee liued, ſo ſhe died; ſhe liued a Saint, and died a Saint: and precious wee know, in the ſight of the Lord is the death of the Saints. In her life ſhee loued and ſerued God, and now being dead ſhee liueth and raigneth vvith the Lord. Of whom I might ſay much, and of whom I can ſay little: much what I haue heard, little, yea nothing what I haue ſeene. For it was not my hap (vvhich I count a great part of my vnhappineſſe) either to ſee her liuing or to heare of her life, before I heard of her death. Her life procured loue, her death, fame: whoſe ſwift wings, more ſwift then the wings of loue, poſſeſſed a great part of the world with her death,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2670:42"/>before it knew of her life. But who could heare of her death, that did not preſently inquire of her life; and who hauing beene informed of her life, did not weepe and mourne for her death: ſo that the hearing of her death, and the hearing of her life, and the weeping and mourning for her death; as in mee, ſo in many met together. Sparing therefore to ſpeake much of her of whom I knew ſo little, and yet willing to ſpeake all good of her of whom I haue heard ſo much, I will ſo temper my ſpeech, that I vvill neither ſpeake too much, nor too little: not too much, becauſe I knew ſo little; not too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, becauſe I haue heard ſo much.</p>
            <p>To begin then where her life began: England, little England, yet farre and greatly renowned England; happie weight to bee borne in ſo renowned a Countrey,
<note place="margin">At <hi>Padley.</hi>
               </note> and happie Countrey to bring forth ſo renowned a weight. Of England in that fruitfull and rich ſhire of Suffolke, rich indeed, in affording the vvorld ſo rich a treaſure: but yet againe moſt poore
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2670:42"/>in the loſſe and want of it. Shall I tell you of her Linage? ancient and worſhipfull, of her education? vertuous and religious: partly vnder a vertuous mother, but for the moſt part vnder an honorable &amp; religious Lady. Shall I tell you of her bodily forme and outward feature, ſo full of grace and beautie, that ſhee procured many vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy louers. Of her externall carriage and behauiour, ſo louing, ſo lowly, ſo inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; that we may rightly ſay of her, ſuch vvas her name, ſuch was her nature; a Lambe in name, and a Lambe in nature <hi>Conueniunt rebus nomina ſaepe ſuis,</hi> ſo name, ſo nature, oftentimes agree. And yet againe in greateſt dangers, perils and feares; in dangers of the Sea, in perils of ſhipwrack, in feares of men of warre, when (as ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it happened) all others in her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie were all at their wits ends, and knew not which way to reſolue to ſinke or ſwimme, to fight or to yeeld: ſhee alone a woman and therefore by ſex feeble, by nature fearefull; yet farre beyond both her nature and her ſexe, remained ſo con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtant,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2670:43"/>ſo bold,
<note place="margin">Daughter to M. Lamb of Padley in Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke.</note> ſo couragious, that ſuch as were preſent in admiration of her ſtoutnes haue confeſſed ſhe rather reſembled a Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then a Lambe. But all this is nothing to the internall vertues and endowments of her mind, theſe alone would require a Panege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Oration, &amp; of theſe I may ſay, as S. <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> vpon the like occaſion ſaid of the holy &amp; religious Matron <hi>Paula, Si cuncta corporis mei me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra verterentur in linguas, &amp; omnes artus humana voce reſonarent, nihil vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſacrae ac venerabilis Paulae virtutibus dicerem:</hi> So may I ſay of this vertuous &amp; religious Lady: If all the members of my body, if my eies, my eares, my hands, my feet, were turned into tongues; &amp; euery arct, veine, nerue, muſcle, that I haue could vtter humane language, I ſhould come farre ſhort of <hi>Annes</hi> worthily deſerued commendations. Therefore lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing this to others who can ſpeak better of them, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their owne knowledge then my ſelf, I come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the manner of her life, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with the manner of her death.</p>
            <p>Of which I againe remember you, that what I ſpeake, I ſpeake not from my ſelfe,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2670:43"/>but from the mouth of ſuch who being eie and eare witneſſes of her actions and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, I preſume haue informed me nothing but the truth. From the time then of her arriuall into this Countrey, ſome of you know, &amp; others may vnderſtand, that it is now full 5. yeeres and ſomwhat more, wherof wanting but a little, ſhe liued vvith the right worſhipfull and worthy Knight her husband, Sir <hi>Thomas Glouer,</hi> then Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Ambaſſador in this Port for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of Great Brittaine, in ſuch great ioy, honor and happineſſe; that the greatneſſe of her contentment oftentimes procured her griefe; knowing that after a great calme their ariſeth a great ſtorme, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of ioy, for the moſt part ends in griefe and dolour. And ſo indeed it happened as ſhe ſuſpected; her ioy ſoone turned into ſorrow, and her health ſuddenly chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into ſickenes. The Saturday ſhe eat, ſhe dranke, ſhe was merrie and pleaſant, the Sunday morning being the thirtieth of <hi>October, Anno.</hi> 1608. ſhe ſickened; the Wenſday following, being the ſecond of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2670:44"/>
               <hi>Nouember,</hi> ſhe dyed one weeke, yea a day, yea an houre, is enough to turne the world vpſide-downe.</p>
            <p>The ſoule of man ſaith the Oratour, before its departure from the bodie, doth oftentimes diuine, and it may bee well thought that the ſoule of this bleſſed La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in her laſt ſickeneſſe had by diuine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration a foreknowledge of her death, in that preſently ſhee deliuered the keyes of her Iewells and the rings from her fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, which in more ſuſpected dangers ſhe was neuer wont to pull off, ſhee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpake mourning garments, and tooke care for her funerall, before her Phyſicians doubted any thing at all of her death, ſhe prefixed a time wherein ſhee ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of this life, ſpeaking verie ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that Wenſday of her death, before the ordinarie houre of ſupper: which time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching ſhe deſired her honorable huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to pray to God vvith her, &amp; for her, which hee did according to the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ordained for the ſicke; which ended, ſhee made a moſt diuine and heauenly
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2670:44"/>praier her ſelfe, wherein ſhee diſcloſed the hidden flames of diuine loue, the euident tokens of a liuely faith, the firme hold of our Sauiours paſſion, for her ſoules re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption with ſuch zeale and feruencie of ſpirit, vttered in words ſo full of diuinitie, and confirmed with action of eies, hands, and ſhrilnes of voice, that it gaue admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble comfort to all that were preſent: vpon which her Phyſician requeſting her then Lord &amp; husband to retire himſelfe a while, &amp; to leaue her to her heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly preparation which otherwiſe by the view of his grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous paſsions might perhaps bee diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, which he hauing done, her Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſtill remaining, ſhe ſaid vnto him, My heart is at eaſe, but I can take no reſt, and therewithall pulling forth her hand, bid him feele her pulſe; which hee told her he found weake, but God was ſtrong and able, if hee pleaſed to reſtore her to her former health. O no, quoth ſhe, I feele it pleaſeth his diuine Maieſtie to diſpoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe of me, hee demanded what ſhee did feele, or where her paine was that hee
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2670:45"/>might adminiſter ſome remedie, I feele no paine: no paine at all ſaid ſhee, but with great ioy I goe cheerefully to my Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus: and therewithall earneſtly called for her Lord, where is he? where is my ſweet heart? where is he? call him quickly, that I may kiſſe him before I die: I pray God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie giue him much ioy, proſperitie and happineſſe. His honour being come, and iudging by her perfect voice, ſpeech and memorie, that ſhee was not neere her death, began to comfort her with truſt in almightie God, that ſhee ſhould haue good remedy and bee reſtored to her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtrength. O no ſweet heart, ſaid ſhe, I draw on to a better world, and doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to goe to my Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus, into whoſe bleſſed hands I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my ſoule. And then ſhe praied and required praiers for her againe: which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, after many redoublings and repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, Into thy hands, O Lord, I doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my ſoule; Into thy hands, O Lord, I doe commend my ſoule, without any
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2670:45"/>grone or ſigh, gently breathing, yeelded vp the ghoſt.</p>
            <p>And thus dyed <hi>Anna,</hi> as dyed <hi>Sarah; Sarah</hi> in her old age, and yet ſo beautifull at a hundred yeeres old, as ſhee was at twentie, ſo ſay the Iewiſh Rabbins, and <hi>Anna</hi> in her young age; and yet ſo vviſe and vertuous at twentie yeeres, as if ſhe had liued an hundreth. <hi>Sarah</hi> dyed in a ſtrange Countrey, farre from her kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and parents: So did <hi>Anna</hi> from hers. <hi>Sarah</hi> in Kiriatharba, vvhoſe founder was <hi>Arba,</hi> and <hi>Anna</hi> in Conſtantinople, whoſe chiefe founder was <hi>Conſtantine. Sara</hi> among the Hittites, and <hi>Anna</hi> among the Turkes. Then <hi>Sarahs</hi> husband came to mourne and weepe for her, and <hi>Annahs</hi> husband is come to mourne and weepe for her. Then <hi>Sarahs</hi> husband roſe vp from the ſight of his corps, hee left off weeping, and ſo ſhould <hi>Annahs</hi> husband too. And <hi>Sarahs</hi> husband prouided a place of buriall for her, and ſo hath <hi>Annahs</hi> husband done for her. What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2670:46"/>now: but as <hi>Sarahs</hi> vvas honourably buried, ſo <hi>Annah</hi> ſhould be buried too. Vp let vs bee going.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2670:46"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
